The question today is not:
السؤال اليوم ليس ..
Why did we invade Afghanistan?
لماذا إجتحنا " أفغانستان " ؟
The question is:
ولكن السؤال هو :
why are we still in Afghanistan
لماذا ما زلنا في " أفغانستان "
one decade later?
بعد عقد من الزمان ؟
Why are we spending
لماذا نصرف
$135 billion?
135 مليار دولار ؟
Why have we got 130,000 troops on the ground?
لماذا لدينا 130 ألف من القوات على الأراضي الأفغانية ؟
Why were more people killed
لماذا قتل عدد أكبر
last month
في الشهر الماضي
than in any preceding month
مما حدث في أي شهر سابق
of this conflict?
طيلة هذا الصراع ؟
How has this happened?
كيف حدث هذا ؟
The last 20 years
في السنوات العشرين الماضية
has been the age of intervention,
كانت سنوات " تدخل صرف في شؤون الدول الأخرى "
and Afghanistan is simply one act
وكانت أفغانستان واحدة من الدول
in a five-act tragedy.
عانت من التدخل الذي مارسناه على خمس مستويات
We came out of the end of the Cold War
لقد خرجنا من الحرب الباردة
in despair.
الى الفراغ ..
We faced Rwanda;
وواجهنا على الفور أزمة راوندا
we faced Bosnia,
و من ثم أزمة البوسنة والهرسك
and then we rediscovered our confidence.
ومن ثم أستعدنا ثقتنا بأنفسنا
In the third act, we went into Bosnia and Kosovo
وفي المستوى الثالث واجهنا أزمة البوسنة وكوسوفو
and we seemed to succeed.
وقد خُيل لنا أننا نجحنا
In the fourth act, with our hubris,
وفي المستوى الرابع إرتقت غطرستنا
our overconfidence developing,
وثقتنا المتزايدة التي دفعتنا
we invaded Iraq and Afghanistan,
لكي نجتاح العراق و أفغانستان
and in the fifth act,
وفي المستوى الخامس
we plunged into a humiliating mess.
غرقنا في فوضى عارمة
So the question is: What are we doing?
مما يطرح تساؤلاً : مالذي نفعله بحق الله ؟
Why are we still stuck in Afghanistan?
لماذا نحن عالقون في أفغانستان ؟
And the answer, of course,
والجواب على هذا هو طبعا
that we keep being given
هو ما يُقال لنا على الدوام
is as follows:
من مريدي تلك الحرب
we're told that we went into Afghanistan
اننا إجتحنا أفغانستان
because of 9/11,
بسبب احداث الحادي عشر من سبتمبر
and that we remain there
وقد بقينا هناك
because the Taliban poses an existential threat
لأن حركة طالبان ما زالت تمثل خطراً قائماً
to global security.
للأمن العالمي
In the words of President Obama,
وبحسب قول الرئيس " اوباما "
"If the Taliban take over again,
" إن استولت طالبان على الحكم ..
they will invite back Al-Qaeda,
فسوف تعيد مجد تنظيم القاعدة
who will try to kill as many of our people
والذي سوف يحاول أن يقتل أكبر عدد ممكن
as they possibly can."
من مواطنينا "
The story that we're told
ان القصة التي تُحكى لنا اليوم
is that there was a "light footprint" initially --
ان هناك نقص في القوات العاملة هناك
in other words, that we ended up in a situation
بمعنى آخر .. لقد بتنا في وضع
where we didn't have enough troops,
لا نملك فيه قوات كافية
we didn't have enough resources,
ولا موارد كافية
that Afghans were frustrated --
وضع .. أحبط الافغان
they felt there wasn't enough progress
وجعلهم يشعرون ان الانجاز ليس كاف
and economic development and security,
وان الاقتصاد و التنمية والامن ليست كافية
and therefore the Taliban came back --
ومن اجل هذا استطاعت طالبان ان تعود الى الساحة
that we responded in 2005 and 2006
والذي تم الرد عليه بإرسال عدد آخر من الجنود في
with troop deployments,
في عام 2005 و 2006
but we still didn't put enough troops on the ground.
وبقينا في حوج الى قوات عاملة على الارض
And that it wasn't until 2009,
حتى عام 2009
when President Obama signed off on a surge,
عندما وقع الرئيس باراك اوباما على زيادة عدد القوات
that we finally had,
وعندها فحسب
in the words of Secretary Clinton,
وبحسب كلمات "هيلاري كلينتون " عن الاولويات
"the strategy, the leadership and the resources."
" الاسترتيجية , القيادة و الموارد "
So, as the president now reassures us,
وتأكيد الرئيس على اننا
we are on track to achieve our goals.
على اننا على الطريق لتحقيق أهدافنا
All of this is wrong.
الا ان كل ذلك كان خاطئاً
Every one of those statements is wrong.
كل تصريح من تلكم التي بني عليها الغزو كان خاطىء
Afghanistan does not
فأفغانستان لا تمثل
pose an existential threat
اي خطر على
to global security.
الامن العالمي
It is extremely unlikely
ومن المستبعد ايضاً
the Taliban would ever be able to take over the country --
ان تستطيع طالبان الإستيلاء على الدولة
extremely unlikely they'd be able to seize Kabul.
بل حتى أن تسيطر على " كابول "
They simply don't have a conventional military option.
فهم ليس لديهم أي خيار عسكري تقليدي
And even if they were able to do so, even if I'm wrong,
ولن يستطيعوا ان يقوموا به .. وحتى ان كنت مخطئاً
it's extremely unlikely
فإنه من غير المرجح ان
the Taliban would invite back Al-Qaeda.
تقوم طالبان بدعوة " القاعدة " للعودة إلى أفغانستان
From the Taliban's point of view,
فمن وجهة نظر حركة طالبان ..
that was their number one mistake last time.
فإن استقبال القاعدة كان خطأئهم الاكبر ..
If they hadn't invited back Al-Qaeda,
فان لم تكن القاعدة في أفغانستان ..
they would still be in power today.
لكانوا مازالوا اليوم على سدة الحكم
And even if I'm wrong about those two things,
وحتى إن كنت مخطئاً في هذين الأمرين
even if they were able to take back the country,
وحتى إن استطاعوا ان يستعيدوا السيطرة على أفغانستان ..
even if they were to invite back Al-Qaeda,
او دعوة القاعدة إلى أفغانستان مجددا
it's extremely unlikely
فانه من غير المرجح
that Al-Qaeda would significantly enhance
ان تستطيع القاعدة ان توفر
its ability to harm the United States
القدرة على إيذاء الولايات المتحدة الامريكية
or harm Europe.
أو الاتحاد الاوروبي
Because this isn't the 1990s anymore.
لان أيام التسعينات ولت
If the Al-Qaeda base
فإن استطاعت القاعدة ان تؤسس قاعدة لها
was to be established near Ghazni,
بالقرب من " غازني "
we would hit them very hard,
فسوف ندكهم دكاً ..
and it would be very, very difficult
وسوف يكون من الصعوبة بمكان
for the Taliban to protect them.
على حركة طالبان أن تحميهم
Furthermore, it's simply not true
والاكثر من هذا فانا لا اعتقد
that what went wrong in Afghanistan
ان الخطأ في أفغانستان
is the light footprint.
كان بسبب نقص العداد البشري للقوات العاملة هناك
In my experience, in fact,
فمن وجهة نظري ..
the light footprint was extremely helpful.
ان نقص العداد البشري كان مساعداً جداً في ضبط الوضع
And these troops that we brought in --
و قوات المشاة التي تم " إستخدامها " في أفغانستان تشابه ..
it's a great picture of David Beckham
صورة هذا الجندي والذي يجلس بالقرب مع " ديفيد بيكهام "
there on the sub-machine gun --
وبالقرب منه مدفعية رشاشة
made the situation worse, not better.
لقد جعل هذا الوضع في أفغانستان أسوء بكثير مما يجب ان يكون عليه
When I walked across Afghanistan
عندما تجولت في أفغانستان
in the winter of 2001-2002,
في شتاء 2001-2002
what I saw was scenes like this.
مارأيته كان هذا ..
A girl, if you're lucky,
فتاة في زاوية غرفة .. ان كانت
in the corner of a dark room --
محظوظة بما فيه الكفاية
lucky to be able to look at the Koran.
لكي تملك الضوء لكي تستطيع أن تقرأ القرآن
But in those early days
ولكن اليوم ..
when we're told we didn't have enough troops and enough resources,
في الوقت التي يخبرونا فيه عن نقص القوات العاملة في أفغانستان
we made a lot of progress in Afghanistan.
فنحن قد حققنا الكثير من التقدم في أفغانستان
Within a few months,
فبعدة أشهر ..
there were two and a half million more girls in school.
كان هناك نصف مليون فتاة في المدارس في أفغانستان
In Sangin where I was sick in 2002,
في سانجين عندما كنت في عام 2002
the nearest health clinic
كانت اقرب عيادة تبعد مسافة سير
was within three days walk.
قدرها 3 ايام
Today, there are 14 health clinics
ولكن اليوم هناك في تلك المنطقة فقط
in that area alone.
14 عيادة
There was amazing improvements.
انها تحسينات كبيرة
We went from almost no Afghans
وقد نقلنا أفغانستان من مرحلة عدم وجود الاتصالات
having mobile telephones during the Taliban
اثناء حكم طالبان في أفغانستان
to a situation where, almost overnight,
الى مرحلة اصبح فيها
three million Afghans had mobile telephones.
في أفغانستان 3 ملايين هاتف محمول
And we had progress in the free media.
وقد حققنا انجازات ايضاً في مجال الاعلام الحر
We had progress in elections --
وقد حققنا انجازات في مجال الانتخابات
all of this with the so-called light footprint.
وكل هذا تم بتلك العداد .. عداد القوات العاملة في أفغانستان
But when we began to bring more money,
ولكن عندما بدأ دفق الاموال يزداد
when we began to invest more resources,
وبدأ الاستثمار يتطور بسرعة
things got worse, not better. How?
ساءت الامور كثيراً .. ولكن لماذا ؟
Well first see, if you put 125 billion dollars a year
إنظروا معي .. حسناً .. ان تم ضخ مايقارب 125 مليار دولار سنوياً
into a country like Afghanistan
في دولة مثل أفغانستان
where the entire revenue of the Afghan state
تلك الدولة التي ميزانيتها لا تتعدى
is one billion dollars a year,
المليار دولار
you drown everything.
فأنت تغرق كل شيء
It's not simply corruption and waste
انه ليس فقط الفساد .. والهدر
that you create;
الذي سيستشري في البلد
you essentially replace the priorities of the Afghan government,
بل انك سوف تستبدل وتغير من اولويات الحكومة الافغانية
the elected Afghan government,
تلك التي تم انتخابها ..
with the micromanaging tendencies
الى اولويات واتجاهات " صغرى "
of foreigners on short tours
تستهدف إرضاء " الجولات " التي يقوم بها الاجانب ..
with their own priorities.
الذين يملكون أولوياتهم الخاصة
And the same is true for the troops.
والامر ذاته ينطبق على الجنود
When I walked across Afghanistan,
عندما تجولت في أفغانستان
I stayed with people like this.
لقد جلست مع أشخاص من مثل ..
This is Commandant Haji Malem Mohsin Khan of Kamenj.
هذا القائد الحجي ماليم محسن خان من كامينج
Commandant Haji Malem Mohsin Khan of Kamenj was a great host.
القائد الحجي ماليم محسن خان كان مضيافاً كثيراً
He was very generous,
وكان فائق الكرم
like many of the Afghans I stayed with.
مثل الكثير من الافغان الذين قضيت معهم الوقت في أفغانستان
But he was also considerably more conservative,
ولكنه يعد من المحافظين
considerably more anti-foreign,
الذين لا يحبذون الاجانب
considerably more Islamist
ويميل الى الاصولية الاسلامية
than we'd like to acknowledge.
اكثر مما كنت أتوقع
This man, for example, Mullah Mustafa,
هذا الرجل على سبيل المثال " الملا مصطفى "
tried to shoot me.
حاول ان يغتالني
And the reason I'm looking a little bit perplexed in this photograph
والسبب الذي أبدو به في هذه الصورة مضطرباً ..
is I was somewhat frightened,
هو انني كنت خائف ..
and I was too afraid on this occasion
خائف من تلك المناسبة التي اجتمعنا فيها
to ask him, having run for an hour through the desert
حيث انه وبعد ان سار بي في الصحراء لمدة ساعة ..
and taken refuge in this house,
واحتجزني في منزله ..
why he had turned up and wanted to have his photograph taken with me.
غير رأيه وقرر ان يتصور معي
But 18 months later, I asked him
وبعد 18 شهراً سألته
why he had tried to shoot me.
لماذا حاولت قتلي ..
And Mullah Mustafa -- he's the man with the pen and paper --
وقد جاوبني الملا مصطفى .. وهو حامل القلم والورقة في الصورة ..
explained that the man sitting immediately to the left as you look at the photograph,
قال لي ان الرجل الذي يجلس على يساري في الصورة
Nadir Shah
نادر شاه
had bet him that he couldn't hit me.
قد تراهن معي على انني لن استطيع اطلاق النار عليك
Now this is not to say
انا لا اشير إلى أن
Afghanistan is a place full of people like Mullah Mustafa.
أفغانستان مليئة بأشخاص مثل الملا مصطفى
It's not; it's a wonderful place
لا أفغانستان ليست كذلك .. انها مكان رائع
full of incredible energy and intelligence.
مليء بالطاقة المميزة والفكر النير
But it is a place
ولكن انها المكان
where the putting-in of the troops
الذي ان تم إرسال المزيد من القوات العسكرية اليه
has increased the violence rather than decreased it.
سوف يزداد العنف بدلا من انخفاضه
2005, Anthony Fitzherbert,
في عام 2005 آنتوني فيتزيربيرت "
an agricultural engineer,
وهو مهندس زراعي
could travel through Helmand,
سافر عبر هلمندآباد
could stay in Nad Ali, Sangin and Ghoresh,
واستقر في " ناد علي و سانجين و جهوريش "
which are now the names of villages where fighting is taking place.
وهي تلك القرى التي يستعر بها القتال اليوم
Today, he could never do that.
واليوم لا يستطيع هو العودة الى تلك القرى
So the idea that we deployed the troops
ان الفكرة التي دفعتنا الى ارسال المزيد من القوات
to respond to the Taliban insurgency
لكي نرد على اعادة نهوض حركة طالبان
is mistaken.
هي فكرة خاطئة
Rather than preceding the insurgency,
فبدلاً من تقويض النهوض
the Taliban followed the troop deployment,
فإن حركة طالبان استجابت لارسال المزيد من القوات بتجنيد المزيد من العناصر
and as far as I'm concerned,
وكما أظن
the troop deployment caused their return.
فان إرسال المزيد من القوات قد ساعد في عودة حركة طالبان إلى الساحة
Now is this a new idea?
ولكن هل ما أقوله فكرة جديدة ؟
No, there have been any number of people
لا .. هناك الكثير من الاشخاص الذين حاججوا في هذا
saying this over the last seven years.
على مدى السنوات السبع الماضية
I ran a center at Harvard
لقد أدرت مركزاً في هارفرد
from 2008 to 2010,
من عام 2008 الى عام 2010
and there were people like Michael Semple there
وكان هناك اشخاص مثل مايكل سيمبل
who speak Afghan languages fluently,
الذي يتحدثون بطلاقة اللغة الافغانية
who've traveled to almost every district in the country.
والذين جالوا في كل مقاطعة من مقاطعات أفغانستان
Andrew Wilder, for example,
وأندرو ويلدر أيضاً على سبيل المثال
born on the Pakistan-Iranian border,
ولد على الحدود الايرانية-الباكستانية
served his whole life
وقد خدم جُل حياته
in Pakistan and Afghanistan.
في باكستان و أفغانستان
Paul Fishstein who began working there in 1978 --
و بول فيشتين والذي بدأ العمل منذ عام 1978
worked for Save the Children,
والذي عمل على انقاذ الاطفال
ran the Afghan research and evaluation unit.
وأدار وحدة البحوث و تقييم الوضع الافغاني
These are people
هؤلاء هم الاشخاص
who were able to say consistently
الذين يقولون على الدوام
that the increase in development aid
ان زيادة المعونات المالية للدولة الأفغانية
was making Afghanistan less secure, not more secure --
تساهم في تقليل مستوى الامن في الدولة
that the counter-insurgency strategy
ان سياسة مكافحة إعادة نهوض طالبان
was not working and would not work.
ليست ناجحة ولن تنجح
And yet, nobody listened to them.
ولكن حتى اليوم لم يستمع إليهم أحد
Instead,
وبدل من ذلك ..
there was a litany of astonishing optimism.
نجد " سياسة وردية " متفائلة
Beginning in 2004,
بدأت منذ بداية عام 2004
every general came in saying,
فكل جنرال حرب يستلم القيادة يقول ..
"I've inherited a dismal situation,
" لقد تسلمت القيادة والوضع سيء جداً ..
but finally I have the right resources and the correct strategy,
ولكني اليوم لدي الامكانيات والاستراتيجة الملائمة
which will deliver,"
لتحسين الوضع "
in General Barno's word in 2004,
انها كلمات الجنرال " برانوا " في عام 2004
the "decisive year."
سنة الحسم
Well guess what? It didn't.
ولكن لم تنجح سياسته ..
But it wasn't sufficient to prevent General Abuzaid saying
ومن ثم قام الجنرال " ابو زيد " بقوله
that he had the strategy and the resources
انه يملك الموارد والاستراتيجية اللازمة لتحسين الوضع
to deliver, in 2005,
في عام 2005
the "decisive year."
ووصف السنة خاصته بسنة الحسم
Or General David Richards to come in 2006
ومن ثم الجنرال ديفيد ريتشارد في عام 2006
and say he had the strategy and the resources
قال أيضاً انه لديه الموارد والاستراتيجية اللازمة لتحسين الوضع
to deliver the "crunch year."
في سنة الأزمة
Or in 2007,
وذات الامر في السنة 2007
the Norwegian deputy foreign minister, Espen Eide,
عندما قال نائب وزير الخارجية النرويجي إيسبن إيدي
to say that that would deliver the "decisive year."
ان السنة تلك ستكون سنة الحسم
Or in 2008, Major General Champoux
وذات الامر تكرر في عام 2008 .. عندما وصف الجنرال تشامبوكس
to come in and say he would deliver the "decisive year."
عندما تسلم القيادة ان سنته ستكون سنة الحسم ..
Or in 2009, my great friend,
وفي عام 2009 قال صديقي الرائع
General Stanley McChrystal,
الجنرال ستانلي ماك كريستال
who said that he was "knee-deep in the decisive year."
ان سنة 2009 هي سنة الحسم بعد أن غرق " الامريكان " حتى الركب في المستنقع الأفغاني
Or in 2010,
وهلمَ جراً حتى 2010
the U.K. foreign secretary, David Miliband,
عندما قال وزير الخارجية البريطانية ديفيد ميليباند
who said that at last we would deliver the "decisive year."
اننا - كقوى التحالف - قد وصلنا الى سنة حسم الموقف في أفغانستان
And you'll be delighted to hear in 2011, today,
وهانحن اليوم وفي عام 2011 لم نطاله بعد ..
that Guido Westerwelle, the German foreign minister,
ولكن وزير الخارجية الالماني جويدو ويسترويلي
assures us that we are in the "decisive year."
أكد ان هذه السنة هي سنة الحسم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
How do we allow
كيف سمحنا لكل
any of this to happen?
هذا أن يحصل ؟
Well the answer, of course, is,
حسناً .. الجواب هو ..
if you spend 125 billion or 130 billion
انه في حال تم صرف 125 مليار .. او 130 مليار
dollars a year in a country,
في أي دولة
you co-opt almost everybody.
فأنت تستميل الجميع ..
Even the aid agencies,
حتى منظمات الإغاثة
who begin to receive an enormous amount of money
تبدأ باستلام كميات هائلة من الاموال
from the U.S. and the European governments
من الحكومة الامريكية والحكومات الاوروبية
to build schools and clinics,
من اجل بناء المدارس والعيادات
are somewhat disinclined
والتي بصورة ما " تنفر "
to challenge the idea
فكرة
that Afghanistan is an existential threat
ان أفغانستان تشكل خطراً حتمياً
to global security.
على الامن العالمي
They're worried, in other words,
فهم - المتبرعون - يخافون بصورة ما
that if anybody believes that it wasn't such a threat --
ان تم الإعتراف بأن أفغانستان لا تشكل خطراً عالمياً
Oxfam, Save the Children
إن منظمة أوكسفام أو إنقاذ الاطفال ..
wouldn't get the money
لن يتلقوا الأموال إن جرى ذلك
to build their hospitals and schools.
ولن تستطيع بناء المستشفيات والمدارس
It's also very difficult to confront a general
وسوف يكون من الصعب ان تواجه ذلك
with medals on his chest.
مع أحد الجنرالات الحربية
It's very difficult for a politician,
انه أمرٌ صعب حتى بالنسبة للسياسيين
because you're afraid that many lives have been lost in vain.
لأنه إن تم ذلك .. فسوف يعي العالم ان العديد من الارواح هدرت دون طائل
You feel deep, deep guilt.
سوف تشعر بذنب كبير ..
You exaggerate your fears,
وسوف تبالغ في مخاوفك ..
and you're terrified about the humiliation
وسوف تهاب الشعور بالاذلال ..
of defeat.
جراء الهزيمة في الحرب تلك .. - في حين انتشرت فكرة ان أفغانستان لم تكن فعلاً خطراً على العالم -
What is the solution to this?
ولكن ماهو الحل لهذه المشكلة ؟
Well the solution to this
حسناً الحل ..
is we need to find a way
هو اننا نحتاج لطريقة ..
that people like Michael Semple, or those other people,
لكي نجعل اشخاصاً مثل " ميشيل سيمبيل " أو أي من الاشخاص الذين ذكرتهم
who are telling the truth, who know the country,
والذين يستطيعون أن يقولوا الحقيقة عن أفغانستان لانهم يعلمون ذلك البلد
who've spent 30 years on the ground --
والذين قضوا اكثر من 30 عاماً في أفغانستان
and most importantly of all,
والاهم من كل ذلك
the missing component of this --
فإن العنصر المفقود من عملية " اعادة الاعمار والتنمية "
Afghans themselves,
هم الافغان نفسهم
who understand what is going on.
والذين يعوون مالذي يجري على أفغانستان
We need to somehow get their message
والذين هم في أمس الحاجة لايصال رسالتهم ووجهة نظرهم
to the policymakers.
لصانعي القرار
And this is very difficult to do
وهذا أمرٌ من الصعب بمكان
because of our structures.
ان يتم جراء سياستنا الحالية
The first thing we need to change
فنحن أولا علينا ان نغير
is the structures of our government.
هيكلية الحكومات لدينا
Very, very sadly,
فللأسف جداً
our foreign services, the United Nations,
ان المنظمات الاجنبية .. والامم المتحدة
the military in these countries
والقوات العسكرية من الدول كافة
have very little idea of what's going on.
ليس لديها اي فكرة عما يجري في أفغانستان
The average British soldier is on a tour of only six months;
ان الجندي البريطاني لا يقضي أكثر من ستة أشهر في أفغانستان
Italian soldiers, on tours of four months;
والإيطالين 4 اشهر
the American military, on tours of 12 months.
والامريكين 12 شهراً
Diplomats are locked in embassy compounds.
والديبلوماسيين محجوزون في السفارات
When they go out, they travel in these curious armored vehicles
وعندما يخرجون .. فانهم يتجولون بمواكب مسلحة
with these somewhat threatening security teams
ومع فرق أمنية مخيفة
who ready 24 hours in advance
والذي يكونون مستعدون قبل 24 ساعة من التحرك
who say you can only stay on the ground for an hour.
والذين يؤمنون فحسب التجول لساعة في أفغانستان
In the British embassy in Afghanistan
ويذكر ان السفارة البريطانية في أفغانستان
in 2008,
في عام 2008
an embassy of 350 people,
كانت تحوي 350 موظفاً
there were only three people who could speak Dari,
فقط ثلاثة منهم كانوا يتحدثون لغة الداري
the main language of Afghanistan, at a decent level.
والتي هي اللغة الرئيسية في أفغانستان
And there was not a single Pashto speaker.
ولم يكن هناك اي شخص يستطيع تحدث لغة البشتون
In the Afghan section in London
في إدارة أفغانستان في خارجية لندن
responsible for governing Afghan policy on the ground,
والذين هم بصورة ما مسئولون عن السياسة الافغانية فعلياً
I was told last year
تم اخباري في العام الماضي
that there was not a single staff member
انه لم يكن هناك اي موظف
of the foreign office in that section
في ذلك المكتب التابع لوزارة الخارجية
who had ever served
قد خدم في أفغانستان
on a posting in Afghanistan.
في أي وظيفة في أفغانستان
So we need to change that institutional culture.
لذا علينا ان نغير ثقافة تلك المؤسسات
And I could make the same points about the United States
وحتما الامر تقريباً ينطبق على الولايات المتحدة
and the United Nations.
والامم المتحدة
Secondly, we need to aim off of the optimism of the generals.
والامر الثاني علينا ان نوقف التفاؤل التام للجنرالات
We need to make sure that we're a little bit suspicious,
علينا ان نفهمهم أننا نشك قليلاً في هذا
that we understand that optimism
نحن نتفهم ان المؤسسة العسكرية
is in the DNA of the military,
تحمل التفاؤل في صلب تحركاتها
that we don't respond to it
ولكن لا يجب ان ينطوي ذلك علينا
with quite as much alacrity.
وان لا يؤثر ذلك على " همتنا " في العمل في أفغانستان
And thirdly, we need to have some humility.
وثالثاً .. نحن بحاجة لقليل من التواضع ..
We need to begin from the position
علينا أن نبدأ من موقع نعي فيه
that our knowledge, our power,
ان معرفتنا .. وقوتنا
our legitimacy
وحتى شرعيتنا .
is limited.
محدودة !
This doesn't mean
وهذا لايعني أن كل " التدخلات " التي
that intervention around the world is a disaster.
جرت حول العالم كانت كارثية
It isn't.
لا ليس كذلك
Bosnia and Kosovo
فالبوسنة وكوسوفو
were signal successes,
كان الامر فيها ناجحٌ جداً
great successes.
نجاح باهر
Today when you go to Bosnia
عندما تذهب اليوم الى البوسنة
it is almost impossible to believe
لن تصدق على الاطلاق ان هذا البلد
that what we saw in the early 1990s happened.
هو ذاته الذي شهد فظائع بداية التسعينيات
It's almost impossible to believe the progress we've made
وانه من المستحيل .. ان تصدقوا كم النجاح والتقدم
since 1994.
الذي حققناه منذ عام 1994
Refugee return,
فقد عاد اللاجئون
which the United Nations High Commission for Refugees
والذي ظنت الهيئة العليا لشؤون اللاجئين
thought would be extremely unlikely,
انه لن يحدث على الاطلاق
has largely happened.
ولكنه حدث وبنطاق واسع
A million properties have been returned.
ولقد تم اعادة اكثر من مليون سكن لأصحابه
Borders between the Bosniak territory
وقد تم ترسيم الحدود
and the Bosnian-Serb territory have calmed down.
بين البوسنة والصرب
The national army has shrunk.
ولقد تقلص عداد الجيش الوطني
The crime rates in Bosnia today
واليوم نسبة الجريمة في البوسنة
are lower than they are in Sweden.
هي أقل من تلك الموجودة في السويد
This has been done
ولقد حدث هذا
by an incredible, principled effort
بسبب الجهود الكبيرة التي تمت
by the international community,
بين المجتمعات الدولية
and, of course, above all,
وطبعاً وفوق كل هذا
by Bosnians themselves.
قد تم ذلك بواسطة البوسنين
But you need to look at context.
ولذلك علينا أن ننظر في النسق العام للأمور
And this is what we've lost in Afghanistan and Iraq.
وهذا ما فقدناه في العراق وأفغانستان
You need to understand that in those places
علينا أن نعي ما تحتاجه حقاً
what really mattered
تلك الدول
was, firstly, the role of Tudman and Milosevic
فمثلاً وصول توجمان وميلوسيفيتش
in coming to the agreement,
الى اتفاق سلام كان عاملاً كبيراً
and then the fact those men went,
ومن ثم انطلاق هؤلاء الرجال
that the regional situation improved,
لتحسين الوضع الاقليمي
that the European Union could offer Bosnia
كما ان عرض الاتحاد الاوروبي للبوسنة
something extraordinary:
العرض المميز
the chance to be part
بأن تكون جزء
of a new thing, a new club,
من شيء جديد .. من نادي جديد
a chance to join something bigger.
فرصة بالانضمام الى شيء كبير
And finally, we need to understand that in Bosnia and Kosovo,
وعلينا في الختام أن نعي .. ان تجربة البوسنة وكوسوفو
a lot of the secret of what we did,
تملك الكثير من الاسرار ..
a lot of the secret of our success,
اسرار نجاحنا واهمها
was our humility --
كان تواضعنا
was the tentative nature of our engagement.
وطبيعة تدخلنا في تلك الدول
We criticized people a lot in Bosnia
كنا ننقد بصورة خاطئة الكثير من الاشخاص في البوسنة
for being quite slow to take on war criminals.
وننقدهم في بطئهم في محاكمة مجرمي الحرب
We criticized them
وننقدهم في بطئهم
for being quite slow to return refugees.
في إعادة اللاجئين
But that slowness, that caution,
ولكن ذلك البطىء .. وذلك الحذر
the fact that President Clinton initially said
وكون الرئيس كيلنتون قرر
that American troops would only be deployed for a year,
ان لا تبقى القوات الامريكية العسكرية العاملة في المنطقة اكثر من عام واحد
turned out to be a strength,
قد انقلب لنقطة قوة
and it helped us to put our priorities right.
وساعد في توظيف وترتيب الاولويات بصورة صحيحة
One of the saddest things
فواحدة من الامور المحزنة
about our involvement in Afghanistan
التي تؤطر تدخلنا في أفغانستان
is that we've got our priorities out of sync.
هو ان أولوياتنا لا تملك اي نسق من التنسيق المشترك
We're not matching our resources to our priorities.
فنحن لا نوازن بين الموارد التي لدينا وبين تلك الاولويات
Because if what we're interested in is terrorism,
فنحن إن كنا مهتمين بكسر شوكة الارهاب
Pakistan is far more important than Afghanistan.
فانا أعتقد ان باكستان هي أكثر أولوية من أفغانستان
If what we're interested in is regional stability,
وان كنا مهتمين بالسلام الاقليمي
Egypt is far more important.
فمصر أكثر اهمية من أفغانستان
If what we're worried about is poverty and development,
وان كنا مهتمين بالفقر والتنمية
sub-Saharan Africa is far more important.
فأفريقيا جنوب الصحراء أكثر أهمية بكثير
This doesn't mean that Afghanistan doesn't matter,
ولكن هذا لايعني أن أفغانستان ليست مهمة
but that it's one of 40 countries in the world
ولكنها واحدة من 40 دولة
with which we need to engage.
تحتاج التدخل الدولي
So if I can finish with a metaphor for intervention,
ويمكنني أن ألخص فكرة التدخل الدولي بمثال
what we need to think of
وهو طريقة يجب علينا أن نفكر فيها
is something like mountain rescue.
وهو ان التدخل الدولي يشبه الانقاذ الجبلي
Why mountain rescue?
لماذا الانقاذ الجبلي ؟
Because when people talk about intervention,
في الحقيقة الناس تتحدث عن التدخل الأجنبي
they imagine that some scientific theory --
كما لو انه نظرية علمية
the Rand Corporation goes around
فمؤسسة راند عندما
counting 43 previous insurgencies
درست 43 تمرداً في السابق
producing mathematical formula
خرجت بمعادلة رياضية
saying you need one trained counter-insurgent
مفادها انه يجب ان يدرب عنصر مضاد للتمرد
for every 20 members of the population.
لكل 20 مواطن
This is the wrong way of looking at it.
ولكن هذا خطأ كبير لفهم المسألة
You need to look at it in the way that you look at mountain rescue.
خاصة عندما ننظر الى سياسة الانقاذ الجبلي
When you're doing mountain rescue,
فعندما ننظر الى الانقاذ الجبلي
you don't take a doctorate in mountain rescue,
فما يحدث هو ان لا يتم " ارسال " فرق " رياضية " او نظرية الى هناك
you look for somebody who knows the terrain.
فما يحدث انه يتم الاستعانة بشخص يعي المنطقة جيداً
It's about context.
ويعي تماما النسق الموجود في الجبال
You understand that you can prepare,
شخص يعي تماما ان الاستعدادات
but the amount of preparation you can do
مهما كانت كبيرة
is limited --
فهي محدودة
you can take some water, you can have a map,
فأنت يمكنك ان تأخذ معك - في فريق الانقاذ - المياه والخرائط
you can have a pack.
والمعدات اللازمة
But what really matters
ولكن ما يهم حقاً
is two kinds of problems --
في عملية الانقاذ نوعان من المشاكل
problems that occur on the mountain
المشاكل التي تحدث في الجبال
which you couldn't anticipate,
والتي لايمكن توقعها
such as, for example, ice on a slope,
مثل سفوح الجبال المرتفعة .. او المجسمات الجليدية
but which you can get around,
والتي يمكن ربما " الالتفاف حولها "
and problems which you couldn't anticipate
والثانية تلك التي لا يمكن توقعها
and which you can't get around,
والتي لايمكن الالتفات حولها
like a sudden blizzard or an avalanche
مثل الانهيارات الثلجية الكبيرة
or a change in the weather.
او التغيرات في المناخ
And the key to this
وطريقة التعامل مع تلك المشاكل
is a guide who has been on that mountain,
هي وجود " مرشد " يعي الجبل جيداً
in every temperature,
ويعي تقلبات درجات حرارته
at every period --
في كل لحظة من لحظات عملية الانقاذ الجبلي
a guide who, above all,
مرشد .. يعي تماما
knows when to turn back,
متى هو الوقت الذي يتوجب علينا العودة فيه والعزوف عن اتمام العملية
who doesn't press on relentlessly
شخص لا يندفع بطيش
when conditions turn against them.
عندما تكون الظروف غير ملائمة
What we look for
نحن نحتاج الى ما يملكه
in firemen, in climbers, in policemen,
رجال الاطفاء والمتسلقين ورجال الشرطة من فكر وسياسات تدخل
and what we should look for in intervention,
اشخاص يعون إلى أين يجب النظر في التدخلات
is intelligent risk takers --
انهم المغامرون الاذكياء
not people who plunge blind off a cliff,
ليس اولئك الذين يطمحون في القفز من الجروف الجبلية
not people who jump into a burning room,
وليس هؤلاء الذين يطمحون للدخول في الغرف المشتعلة دون وعي
but who weigh their risks,
ولكن نحتاج من يستطيع الموازنة بين المخاطر
weigh their responsibilities.
والموازنة بين المسؤوليات
Because the worst thing we have done in Afghanistan
لأن اسوأ شيء قمنا به في افغانستان
is this idea
هو هذه الفكرة
that failure is not an option.
بأن الفشل ليس خياراً
It makes failure invisible,
ان طريقة التفكير تلك تهمش الفشل
inconceivable and inevitable.
وتجعله بعيداً عن تصورنا وتوقعنا
And if we can resist
وان استطعنا أن نقاوم
this crazy slogan,
هذه " النرجسية " الفكرية
we shall discover --
سوف نكتشف
in Egypt, in Syria, in Libya,
انه في مصر و سوريا وليبيا
and anywhere else we go in the world --
وفي كل مكان في العالم
that if we can often do much less than we pretend,
انه ان استطعنا ان " نتأمل " أقل مما نتأمله اليوم " بتعنت "
we can do much more than we fear.
سوف نستطيع أن نقوم بالكثير وأن ننجز أكثر بكثير من تلك الاهداف التي تقوضها مخاوفنا
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Rory, you mentioned Libya at the end.
برونو جيوساني : روي .. لقد ذكرت مايحدث في ليبيا في نهاية محادثتك
Just briefly, what's your take on the current events there
بصورة مقتبضة .. ماهو تعليقك على الاحداث التي تجري هناك
and the intervention?
وعلى طبيعة التدخل في ليبيا ؟
Rory Stewart: Okay, I think Libya poses the classic problem.
روي ستيورات : أعتقد أن ليبيا هي مشكلة كلاسيكية
The problem in Libya
المشكلة في ليبيا
is that we are always pushing for the black or white.
اننا نطرح على الدوام حلول " بيضاء أو سوداء "
We imagine there are only two choices:
فإننا دوماً نتصور أن هناك فقط خياران
either full engagement and troop deployment
اما تدخل عسكري تام
or total isolation.
او عزلة دولية تامة
And we are always being tempted up to our neck.
فنحن على الدوام ننظر إلى نهاية التدخل والخيار الذي نقوم به
We put our toes in and we go up to our neck.
ما إن تطال اقدامنا المشكلة حتى نفكر على الفور في النهاية
What we should have done in Libya
ما يجب ان يحدث في ليبا
is we should have stuck to the U.N. resolution.
هو ان نلتزم بسياسة الامم المتحدة
We should have limited ourselves very, very strictly
وعلينا أن نقوض تدخلنا بصورة حازمة
to the protection of the civilian population in Benghazi.
من اجل حماية الشعب في بنغازي
We could have done that.
يمكننا القيام بذلك
We set up a no-fly zone within 48 hours
فقد اقمنا منطقة حظر تجول فوق تلك المدينة خلال 48 ساعة
because Gaddafi had no planes
لان القذافي لا يملك سلاح طيران
within 48 hours.
استغرق ذلك فحسب 48 ساعة
Instead of which, we've allowed ourselves to be tempted
وما أن قمنا بذلك إنجرفنا على الفور
towards regime change.
نحو المطالبة بتغير النظام
In doing so, we've destroyed our credibility with the Security Council,
وبذلك قوضنا شرعيتنا مع مجلس الامن
which means it's very difficult
الذي يعني أن الأمر سيصبح صعبا
to get a resolution on Syria,
لنلقى إجماع على قرار من الأمم المتحدة بشأن سوريا
and we're setting ourselves up again for failure.
ونحن نجهز أنفسنا مجدداً للفشل
Once more, humility,
أشدد مرة أخرى على التواضع
limits, honesty,
والحدود والصدق
realistic expectations
والتوقعات المنطقية
and we could have achieved something to be proud of.
التي ستمكننا من انجاز انجازات نفتخر بها
BG: Rory, thank you very much.
برونو جيوساني : روي شكراً لك جزيلاً
RS: Thank you. (BG: Thank you.)
روي ستيورات : شكراً لك ( برونو جيوساني : شكراً لك )